Friends with Brews!
Hi, I'm Scott, and this is, well, as you just heard, Friends with Brews!
Today's gonna be a little bit different. I don't have a Peter Nikolaidis with me today,
because Peter is doing security-related training, or he's getting certainI don't know what he's doing.
But anyway, yes, I understand that what you're about to hear is going to be a solo podcast,
and those are usually boring because what you get is some monotone guy droning on and on,
And, you know, it sounds like either they're reading something or just sounds like they
are talking to themselves and nobody, no one, sounds interesting when they talk to themselves.
Despite what some people I know think. It just doesn't work. But anyway, I'm gonna try my best.
I have some things to talk about. We're just gonna carry on.
Aren't you going to introduce me? I'm here and I'm your friend. In fact, I'm your best friend.
Hey, Peter, it's you. I'm glad you're here, man.
Hi, Peter.
Let's record.
I'm Neter Pikolaidis and I have stuff to talk about and things to drink. Okay, Neter Pikolaidis
If that is your real name, I'm gonna start with my drink
I have a coffee today and it's water Avenue coffee, which we've talked about before on this podcast and
It's there a Portland roaster
This one's called river trip and it is a bit of a trip looking at the bag because it's like blue and purple
with yellow labels yellow on the label yellow back label and
Their river trip coffee is a yearly. It's a seasonal and they call it their yearly homage to summer
they say a clean and bright cup that perfectly complements a morning sun peeking over canyon walls a combination of a
Combination of seasonal fresh coffees from our longest standing partners in Guatemala and Africa
The tasting notes are Peter you'll be pleased to hear this orange macadamia nut and fudge sickle like chocolate
And I gotta say okay, so on the back they've got a label that has a
Roast level chart and it's between medium and light but more towards the medium
They've got a taste profile chart that get this it goes from classic
Complex and out there and it's in the out there territory. It's not all the way at the end of the range, but it's up there
I don't know. I don't think it's that far out there. I think it's good
Do I taste all the things that they said in their tasting notes? I don't know. Maybe I'm not that sophisticated
I don't I don't but it's good. I like it. It's a good combination. This is not that far out there
So if you live in Portland, Oregon or anywhere that happens to get Water Avenue coffees and if you see River Trip
Don't be scared buy it. You'll like it. I like it. So yeah, there you go. What about you? I'm Neter Pikolaidis
I am NOT an AI but if I was an AI I would not be able to drink but if I were drinking
I'd probably drink something from Ommegang Brewery, most likely something with tons of chocolate in it.
Okay, you're really... all right, Peter. I'm not gonna argue.
I'm Neater Pickle-latest.
All right, let's just move on to the topic. Since you're so friggin obsessed with AI this week,
I think it's appropriate that I wanted to talk about AI.
I wanted to talk about how I use AI, how I use ChatGPT, because I want to clarify
where do I find it to be useful, where do I think it's not useful, and just some of the
things that I've been listening to and reading about it because I think there's a gold rush.
We saw it with cryptocurrency.
We see how things go when tech bros get a hold of some shiny new toy.
And the problem is that there are limitations to large language models and the fact that
they're being generally applied to everything.
And I think it's okay to consider that.
A gold rush is a period of feverish migration of people to an area that has had a discovery of gold deposits.
Typically, the gold rush is characterized by a sudden and rapid influx of miners seeking their fortune in the newly discovered gold fields.
Gold rushes have occurred in various parts of the world, including California in 1849, Australia in the 1850s, South Africa in the late 1800s, and Alaska in the late 1800s and early 1900s.
1900s gold rushes have had a significant impact on the
development of many regions including the growth of cities the establishment of new businesses and the creation of new
technologies for mining and processing gold
Thank You Rainman, but seriously, don't you have some feeling don't you have some impression of?
what large language models are best used for because you must understand based on how they work
that there are applications that they're entirely unsuited for or at the very least that they're going to be
inaccurate at ranging from slightly inaccurate to wildly inaccurate and
You have to be the one that has to be able to tell the difference
Large language models are as accurate as the information they're given only the best people are working on large language model AI
only the best people are providing training data and only the best data is
Given to the large language models by those best people. I understand your concerns, but well, no, I don't understand your concerns
All right. Well, first of all, let's talk about those people since you went there. Let's talk about that
What do you have? What do you have in common? What do you have in common with Sam Altman?
Let's look at him compared to Elon Musk Mark Zuckerberg Jack Dorsey. What it what all those guys have in common?
Yes, they're guys. They're white friggin guys. They're very I mean Zuckerberg's not even
He's barely human. I mean look at his facial expressions. Okay, so you've got a lot of guys that are very monoculture
They believe that they're doing they right they believe that they're changing friggin society for the best based on what?
Social media most of them now AI and large language models aren't social media
But they are a thing that is being used in the same way in that
people read the stuff that comes out of it and they believe it. It affects their thinking.
Now, that's fine if they're getting accurate information out of it, but they're not.
And that goes back again to how large language models work.
Okay, but before we go there, because you did talk about the people,
Let's look at examples of people, diverse people, people of other backgrounds in AI
with knowledge and how they've been treated when they say, "We need to make sure that
we understand how to correct for the inherent biases that AI are going to have based on
the training data they're being given," which is from the internet, which is inherently
biased.
like Timnit Gebru.
She was working at Google and she brought up concerns
and she wrote a paper about ethical AI generation
and she was asked by Google to remove the names
of the Google people from the paper
and she did not want to do that.
She said, "No, she's not just gonna remove the names."
Google let her go.
They claimed they were accepting her resignation,
but it's not clear that she resigned.
she said she was fired.
Now, this is not unusual behavior
in how people who raise the alarms are treated
when they bring up issues of AI.
And in fact, other women have brought up concerns
about bias in AI and the need
to take the diversity issue very seriously,
and they've been tormented online,
like they've been attacked.
So already you have that issue.
That is issue number one.
people. If the people involved in helping create this technology are themselves assholes,
then how are we to trust, how are we to trust, you know, that they're inherently doing the
right thing? The best people, you say, maybe the best technically, but not the best socially.
Please cite your sources. Did you get this from Wikipedia? Wikipedia is on the internet
and it is inherently biased. Wikipedia sources are people who have a very specific point
of view on the topics they write about, otherwise they would not be writing about them.
Let's listen to a clip of Timnit Gebru from Tech Won't Save Us podcast.
It's an episode called "Don't Fall for the AI Hype."
For me, we can never have a utopia that is, you know, based on the vision of some homogeneous
group that, you know, has absolutely no ground in history or they don't understand art even.
You know what I'm saying?
Like, I'm, you know, I used to play piano for a long time and I, you know, I'm a dancer
and I don't, you know, I'm not a visual artist.
My goal is not to watch a robot dance even if they end up doing technically things that
are, you know, whatever technique is just one aspect of it's like having words.
It's a communication mechanism between humans, right?
It's a human expression mechanism.
People use art for social movements.
People use – I just – you know what I'm saying?
So these are the people who want to give us techno-utopian.
I don't know what it even means.
Like a world where you just sit at your computer all the time, you never interact with other
human beings, everything you do is like with a chatbot and with a robot and with – I
mean, why do I want to live in that world, honestly?
So even their vision, which won't happen, is dystopian.
I just don't see how this is utopia.
But you keep talking about technical limitations of large language models.
I, being interested in large language models, would like to hear why you think they're so
technically limiting.
Are you not, frankly, impressed by how well they generate answers and how much they know
and how able they are to communicate in an extremely human fashion, including accepting
and understanding the necessarily imprecise prompts they're given in human language?
Yes, of course, and they are impressive in that way.
But the difference between ... You say human-like, and that's true in terms of how they output
and the input, the grammar, the text, the prompts that they can take.
But they're not human-like in that they don't understand the veracity of what they're saying,
They don't know how to judge its accuracy.
So anything that's in their training data can come out, whether it's accurate or not.
It just has to meet a giant probability exercise for what is the correct response to the prompt
based on training data, here's the information.
There's no judgment as to accuracy or precision in those answers.
So that's the problem.
It's not the problem of, "Wow, they do a really good job of understanding and speaking my
language."
Yeah, they do.
But they also just make stuff up sometimes or think things are true that aren't true
because they aren't made to evaluate truth and to be knowledge repositories.
I just got done reading a book by Stephen Wolfram, who's the Wolfram Alpha guy, and
The book is called "What is ChatGPT Doing and Why Does It Work?"
And he goes into very great detail about this language model thing and how it works and
how it predicts the next word that it needs to come up with, and talking about the neural
nets and how it's actually quite surprising that it comes up with language in ways that
are similar to humans.
in fact, given a lot less neurons in the neural network than you would think, and it does
a good job.
But he, of course, has a service to pimp, Wolfram Alpha, and what he is advocating is
tying chatGPT to something like that, so that it has factual data to give people, so that
it can do what it's best at, aka say things in a reasonable human way, but not be expected
to do things that it's bad at, like facts, and that it can have a factual repository
of information that it can rely upon.
And I don't know if it's Wolfram Alpha, I don't know what, but there have to be various
different sources that are going to be tied to these large language models.
The large language model is kind of like the API, if you will, to the entire system, or
it should be, I should say.
But it's actually being used as the entire system right now for factual-based things
that it really isn't good at.
In order for people to be factually accurate, they must be able to consult information.
And depending on the person and the veracity of the information they rely on, they also
may be no more accurate than you say large language models tend to be.
By the way, it is widely suspected that Steven Wolfram is a form of artificial intelligence,
albeit one that is trained for math and science and not for human interaction.
I believe the point about Stephen Wolfram, but the difference between humans and large
language models is that humans can make their own evaluation as to not only the veracity
of information, but the veracity of other human beings and whatever information those
human beings are spewing out.
So that is a difference.
Uh, I would like to know more about some of these people who you say are knowledgeable
critics of large language models, uh, being used as general purpose AI so that I can track
them down, I mean so that I can request more training data.
A really good one is a linguist named Emily Bender and she has been on different podcasts
like Tech Won't Save Us.
She has written a paper called "A Really Good One of Stochastic Parrots" and she has been
featured in New Yorker and yeah and she's written posts aimed at policymakers talking
about AI hype.
He's very good at understanding the difference between what a large language model is good
for and what it isn't, and the problem of hype, because human beings fall for hype,
and human beings will fall for implementing and relying on a tool that really can't do
what they want it to do.
And when AI that isn't capable of doing so is used to make decisions about other people,
such as crime prediction or sentence determination or, you know, "Should I rent to this person
or any number of topics, then it starts becoming problematic.
And these are the kinds of things that Emily addresses.
I don't think using GitHub Copilot is going to send anyone to jail.
And it's certainly not being used to predict crime.
Well, unless you consider most JavaScript frameworks to be a form of crime, which I
kind of do, having been shown many examples of them in a short period of time.
Well, you do bring up a good point there that ChatGPT and other large language models aren't
the first instance of a technology that has been abused beyond its breaking point.
So I'll give you that one.
Here are some examples of misapplications of technology in history.
1.
Atomic bombs.
The atomic bombs dropped on Hiroshima and Nagasaki in 1945 were a devastating example
of the misapplication of technology.
The bombs caused massive destruction and loss of life and their use has been controversial
ever since.
2.
Thalidomide was a drug developed in the 1950s to treat morning sickness in pregnant women.
However, it was later discovered that the drug caused severe birth defects in thousands of babies.
3. DDT. DDT was a pesticide widely used in the mid 20th century to control insects and disease.
However, it was later discovered that DDT was harmful to the environment and wildlife,
and its use was banned in many countries.
4. Nuclear power plant disasters.
The Chernobyl and Fukushima nuclear disasters were both caused by failures in technology and
human error. These disasters caused significant environmental damage and loss of life.
5. Social media. While social media has many benefits, it has also been misused to spread
misinformation, cyberbullying, and hate speech. The misuse of social media has led to many negative
consequences, including political polarization and social unrest.
Congratulations Rainman, and I'm not going to look up all those dates to see if they're
accurate or not and let's just assume for the sake of argument here that what you're saying is true.
That's fine, that's great. That doesn't negate the fact that we don't want to allow AI to be
used in ways that is non-beneficial, where the term non-beneficial, instead of having one specific
meaning, ranges anywhere from leads someone slightly askew to gets people killed. Or even
worse, messes up your CSS grid so that visitors to your website can't find the navigation menu?
Exactly. I mean, no, not... Yes, that happens too. No, please don't compare those things.
Okay, look, the whole point of this episode was not to argue... It's not to fight about whether
or not large language models are any good, whether or not we should have this technology. That's not
my point. My point is there are downsides to trying to use them as general purpose AIs and
and having people trust them for things that they're not very good at being accurate about.
Also because of the type of interaction and because they're so good at language, which,
hey, that's what they're designed for, you know, people can trust them and rely on them
more than they ought to.
And in fact, there are, you know, chatbots, AI chatbots, large language model chatbots
being used for therapy or for talking to people who need some kind of advice.
And that gets risky fast if the people forget that they're talking to an AI and forget that
they need to be careful in terms of just doing whatever it says or believing whatever it
says or accepting whatever it says at face value.
Yeah.
Anyway, I don't want to end on a downer.
What I want to say is, you know, one of the more interesting interviews that I've listened
to recently was on the Decoder podcast with Nilay Patel, and he was interviewing Microsoft
CTO Kevin Scott.
And Kevin Scott has, as they put it in the podcast, the entire GPU budget of Microsoft
at his disposal.
The GPU budget necessarily means everything that's AI-related at Microsoft, and they talk
about that. And so that was a good episode and I liked it. And Kevin Scott to me comes
across as a guy who is realistic about the limitations of the technology and focusing
it to get it to do the things that it's good at. Having said that, Microsoft also rolled
out basically ChatGPT into Bing, and they were surprised when it wanted Kevin Roos to
leave his wife. So there's that. Anyway, let's listen to just a little bit of that that I
I found interesting.
So one more on this line, and I do really want to ask about the structure of your
partnership with OpenAI, um, decoder stuff.
You've got a training data feedback loop problem coming, not tomorrow, maybe not
next year or so, but right now these models are trained off a bunch of stuff
that people have put on the web, that people have put in the GitHub, that
people have put everywhere.
Yep.
The volume of output from these systems, from these copilots is voluminous, right?
It's going to quickly dwarf the amount of human
output that is on the Internet.
>> Yep.
>> And then you're going to train against that.
And that feels like a feedback loop that will lead
to weird outcomes if not controlled for.
How do you think about that?
>> So, look, we've had some pretty good techniques
for a while now to assess the quality of data
that we're feeding into these systems so that
you're not, you know, training things on low-quality data.
I think many of those techniques will work here and,
like, might even be easier to apply.
And then another thing that I think we will be doing,
like, I think real soon, either by convention of all
of the people in tech or because it becomes a
regulatory requirement, like, you're going to have to
figure out some way or another to mark that a piece
of content is AI-generated. We're going to announce
some stuff that build around this. Like, we've for
three years now been working on like a media
provenance system that lets you put an invisible
cryptographic watermark and manifest into audio and
visual content so that when you get this content,
like you can have a piece of software decrypt the
manifest and the manifest says like, "This is where
I came from and it's useful for disinformation detection in general.
You can say as a user,
I only want to consume content whose provenance I understand.
You could say I don't want to consume content that is AI-generated.
If you are building a system that is ingesting this content to train,
you can look at the manifest and say,
this is synthetic content,
probably shouldn't be in the training data.
>> So, I just saw Sundar Pichai at Google's
developer conference.
>> Yep.
>> They've got the same idea.
>> I'll make the same threat to you.
If you want to come back and talk about metadata
for an hour, I will do it at the drop of a hat.
>> Yeah, yeah.
I would actually -I think it's a really important
thing, and I think, yeah, there are a bunch of
long-term problems and short-term problems with AI.
There are hard problems.
There are easy problems.
Like, the provenance one seems like a thing that
we ought to be able to go solve.
And I think —
>> Yeah.
We got to — here's what we're going to do.
We're going to rent a theater.
We're going to sell drinks.
And we're going to sit and drink with, like — I guarantee you, it'll be like an
audience of thousands of people who want to drink through a metadata conversation.
That's just what I know.
>> Anyway, I just found that kind of interesting.
And you know, discussions of some of the problems, obviously, the initial round of training data
is bad enough without having other AI stuff thrown into it.
So it's a valid problem.
That's one of the reasons I like Decoder anyways, because Nilay Patel tends to think of that
kind of stuff.
Okay, do you have anything else on your mind, or should we get out of here?
What else do you have?
I have nothing else to say to you.
Well, okay then.
I have nothing to say to you either.
Except, tell people how to find us.
You can find us at friendswithbrews.com, you can find me at 11labs.io, where Scott
synthesized me from a recording of Peter.
You can find Scott on Mastodon at appdot.net/@scottaw.
Ha! That always makes me laugh, but never mind that. Just ask your local friendly AI to help you.
I'm sure it knows more than Scott.
And now it's time to push the big red AI button!